Alessandro Rossini, PhD

IT, Enterprise Architecture, Cloud Transformation, Research and Innovation

☑ me@alessandrorossini.org வ alessandrorossini.org

Oslo, Norway

Alessandro Rossini is a Senior Manager at PwC Consulting in Oslo, Norway. He has more than 14 years of experience in information technology.

Alessandro's expertise spans enterprise and solution architecture, cloud and collaboration platforms, model-driven software engineering, IT governance, and research and innovation. Thanks to his interdisciplinary background, he has a successful record of accomplishments in both industry and academia.

In his current position, Alessandro helps organizations digitalize their business capabilities, modernize their technology platforms, and improve their governance processes to achieve increased efficiency and innovation. He works closely with C-level executives and relevant stakeholders.

Alessandro holds a Ph.D. in computer science from the University of Bergen, Norway. He has more than 40 peer-reviewed scientific publications as well as several articles in the media. His certifications include TBM Executive, PRINCE2 Agile, TOGAF 9, AWS, and Azure.

Alessandro has lived in three countries and speaks English, Norwegian, Italian, and Spanish. His colleagues describe him as analytical, creative, and goal-oriented.

Experience

Senior Manager, Business Technology, PwC Consulting, Oslo, Norway

2018-Present

Subject matter expert and project manager in various engagements on enterprise architecture, cloud transformation, IT governance, and technology due diligence at clients in the public and private sectors (see Projects below). Coordinating the collaboration with research institutions. Lecturing on cloud and collaboration platforms. Career coach for junior colleagues.

Chief Advisor, Digital Platform Services, EVRY (now TietoEVRY), Oslo, Norway

2017-2018

Subject matter expert on cloud services in bids and projects with third-party vendors. Developing the service portfolio of cloud and cognitive services. Coordinating the collaboration with research institutions. Teaching the writing course and chairing the editorial board of the unit. Lecturing on enterprise architecture and project experiences at EVRY Academy.

Research Scientist, Dep. of Software and Service Innovation, SINTEF, Oslo, Norway

2012-2017

Research on model-driven engineering and cloud computing. Project manager and work package leader in EU-and SINTEF-funded projects (see Projects below). Technical committee member of the OASIS Topology and Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications (TOSCA) and co-chair of the TOSCA Instance Model Ad Hoc group. Organizing and program committee member in international conferences and workshops. Supervision of students in the context of Master thesis and internship.

Lecturer, Dep. of Electrical and Electronic Eng., Bergen University College, Norway	2012
Guest Researcher, Dep. of Computer Science, Universidad Autónoma de Madrid, Spain	2011
Research Fellow, Dep. of Informatics, University of Bergen, Norway	2008-2011
Software Engineer, Integrator, Bergen, Norway	2007
Software Engineer, ZeroNotice, L'Aquila, Italy	2005-2007
Software Engineer, IgTechnology (now Indra), Roma, Italy	2005

Projects

Health Analytics Platform, The Norwegian Directorate of eHealth

2020-Present

The Norwegian Directorate of eHealth established the Health Data Program for contributing to better health research and more knowledge-based health services through better utilization and quality of Norwegian health data. This program is developing the Health Analytics Platform, which consists of a data platform with copies of data from the country's health registries, along with an ecosystem of analytics tools.

As **Subject Matter Expert**, Alessandro has been responsible for: estimating fixed and variable costs for the operation of the Health Analytics Platform; identifying technical and commercial measures for cost reduction; defining financing and governance models for the operation of the Health Analytics Platform.

Operation and Development Platform, The Norwegian Tax Administration

2018-2020

The Norwegian Tax Administration established a set of strategic measures in IT to put the organization in the best possible position to develop, manage, and operate IT services. One of these measures was to assess the cloud as the primary operation and development platform for the Norwegian Tax Administration.

As **Subject Matter Expert** and **Project Manager**, Alessandro contributed to: defining a strategy, governance model, learning plan, and target architecture; establishing a framework agreement for cloud services and evaluating offers from the market; charting and assessing applications, platform, and infrastructure; cost analysis of platform and infrastructure on-premises; cost estimation of migrating to public cloud and collaboration platforms; establishing a framework for cost categorization based on Technology Business Management.

Technical Due Diligences, multiple private companies

2019-202

A technology due diligence (Tech DD) offers an independent evaluation of the technology in an enterprise, often in the context of mergers and acquisitions. PwC has performed Tech DDs for private companies in the services, IT, energy, oil and gas, maritime, and real estate sectors.

As **Subject Matter Expert**, Alessandro has been responsible for assessing strengths, weaknesses, and red flags within: digital strategy, roadmap and portfolio; IT organization; IT governance and sourcing; architecture and technology stack; cloud, infrastructure and platform; insights and automation; cyber security.

Cloud Management Platform, EVRY	2017-2018
ARCADIA, European Commission's H2020 Programme	2014-2016
PaaSage, European Commission's 7 th Framework Programme	2012-2016
Broker@Cloud, European Commission's 7 th Framework Programme	2012-2016
DPF , University of Bergen and Bergen University College	2008-2012
ZNF , Self-funded	2005-2007
Education	
Philosophiae Doctor (Ph.D.), Dep. of Informatics, University of Bergen, Norway	2011
Master of Science (M.Sc.), Dep. of Computer Science, Università degli Studi dell'Aquila, Italy	2006
Certifications	
AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner	2020
Azure Fundamentals	2020
Certified Technology Business Management Executive (CTBME)	2020
TOGAF 9 Foundation	2019
PRINCE2 Agile Practitioner in Agile Project Management	2019
Courses	
Business Outcome Enablement, Global Knowledge, Oslo, Norway	2017
Research Methodology, SINTEF School, Trondheim, Norway	2013
LASER Summer School on Empirical Software Engineering, ETH, Zürich, Switzerland	2010

Languages

Italian: Native proficiency

English, **Norwegian**: Full professional proficiency

Spanish: Limited working proficiency

Personal interests

Science, Technology, Traveling, Photography, Languages, Communication, Food, Wine, Movies, Music, Hiking

Publications

40+ publications in peer-reviewed conference proceedings and journals.